

# Nick Lauersdorf

Computational Physicist and Data Scientist



(608) 852-6337

ttps://www.njlauersdorf.com

njlauersdorf@gmail.com

# Social Network

RG

ResearchGate Link



https://github.com/njlauersdorf

# Languages

Python

MATLAB

C++

HTML

CSS

Javascript

SQL

## Tools

HOOMD-Blue
Mathematica
Model Development
Tableau
Scikit-learn
Seaborn
Pytorch
Tensorflow
OpenCV
Django

## Interests

Video Games
Comic Collecting
Film

## **Objective**

Computational Physicist seeking to apply 9-years of modeling and simulation, data science, and software development experience to a career in industry. Extensive experience developing physics-based models, writing algorithms to statistically analyze big data, and designing intuitive visualizations to share significant findings.

## Education

#### PhD in Materials Science | UNC-Chapel Hill

2019 - 2024

- Graduate Certificate in Innovation, Leadership, & Management
- Fully paid for 3-years of graduate career by winning the Department of Defense (DoD) National Defense Science & Engineering Graduate (NDSEG) Fellowship

### B.S. in Physics and Mathematics | UW-Madison

2014 - 2018

• GPA: 3.60

## Experience

### Research & Programming

## Computational Physicist | UNC-Chapel Hill

2020 - current

- Discovered meta-stable states of phase separation (clustering) for active Brownian particle mixtures via C++ molecular dynamics simulations [Published in 2023]
- Determined phase boundary between stable and meta-stable clusters by training logistic regression machine learning model [Published in 2023]
- Allowed differentiation of bulk and interface of cluster by writing local translational and orientational order-based clustering algorithm
- Enabled design of active matter steady-states by deriving predictive statistical mechanics theory [Published in 2021]

### Data Scientist | BeAM Makerspaces

2019 - 2021

- Enabled cost-efficient scheduling and targeted marketing by developing Tableau workbooks for statistical analysis of user demographics and makerspace usage
- Improved end-user experience of staff by leading beta testing of BeAM user analytics software
- Increased BeAM monthly first-time users by 15% by designing marketing visualizations for UNC's websites and within every UNC makerspace
- Led team that created and implemented a campus-wide BeAM inventory tracking system and Salesforce database

#### Experimental Physicist | UNC-Chapel Hill

2019 - 202

 Expanded lab's presence by forming and managing a collaboration network with numerous national labs

#### Assistant Scientist | Pharmaeutical Product Development

2018 - 2019

• Increased customer satisfaction by writing reports following GMP and FDA requirements

#### Computational Physicist | UW-Madison

2016 - 2018

- Enabled accurate prediction of fusion plasma properties by developing a Bayesian statistics model in Python
- $\bullet$  Increased efficiency of model by 40% through converting iterations over lists to multi-dimensional tensor mathematics
- Enabled user-friendly design of x-ray detector optics by developing multi-variable optimization routines to maximize signal
- Increased measurement capabilities of scientists by designing x-ray detector that removes undesirable noise from measurements [Published in 2018]

### Teaching & Mentoring

#### STEM Mentor | Junior Science & Humanities Symposium

2022 - current

• Won \$20,000 for two mentees' college funds by placing second overall at nationals with computer vision, machine learning, and data science research projects

### Teaching Assistant | UNC-Chapel Hill

2020 - 2021

- Introduced others to programming by leading lectures on MATLAB and Python
- Designed molecular dynamics models by overseeing research projects

## Awards

NDSEG Research Fellowship [\$180,000] | Department of Defense 2021 – 2024

First Place Presentation | Triangle Student Research Competition 2021

Theodore Herfurth Scholarship [\$40,000] | UW-Madison 2014 – 2018